You've probably guessed what they are --
لربما أنكم خمنتم عن ماذا سأتحدث
data and history.
البيانات والتاريخ
Right?
أليس كذلك؟
So, I'm not a historian.
أنا لست عالم تاريخ
I'm not going to give you a definition of history.
وأنا لن أعطيكم تعريفا للتاريخ.
But let's think instead of history within a framework.
لكن فلنفكر بدلا عن ذلك بالتاريخ ضمن إطار.
So, when we're making history,
لذلك، عندما نصنع التاريخ
or when we're creating historical documents,
أو نستنبط الوثائق التاريخية
we're taking things that have happened in the past,
فنحن نسترجع ما حدث في الماضي
and we're stitching them together into a story.
ونحيكهم ضمن قصة واحدة
So let me start with a little bit of my own story.
لذا دعوني أبدأ بالتحدث قليلا عن قصتي
Like anybody my age who works creatively with computers,
كأي شخص في نفس عمري يستخدم أجهزة الحاسوب ببراعة،
I was a popular, socially well-adjusted young man --
كنت شاباَ محبوباً، ومتأقلم اجتماعيا‘
(Laughter)
(َضحك)
And sporty!
ورياضي أيضا!
Sporty young man.
شاب رياضي
And like a lot of people my age in the type of business that I'm in,
وكالعديد من الأشخاص في سني ممن يعملون في نفس المجال،
I was influenced tremendously by Apple.
كنت متاثراً جداً بشركة "أبل"
But notice my choice of logo here, right?
لكن، هل لاحظتم الشعار الذي اخترته هنا؟
The Apple on the left, not the Apple on the right.
شعار"أبل" الموجود جهة اليسار وليس اليمين
I'm influenced as much by the Apple on the right
أنا متأثرأيضا بالشعارالذي على اليمين
as the next person,
كالشخص التالي
but the Apple on the left -- I mean, look at that logo!
لكنني أعني شعار أبل جهة اليسار انظروا إليه
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That's how crazy Apple was.
هذا يظهر كم كانت "أبل" مجنونة
But I don't want to talk too much about the company.
لكني أنا لا أريد التحدث عن الشركة كثيراَ
I'll start talking about a machine, though.
سأبدأ بالتحدث رغم ذلك عن آلة ما
How amazing it is to think about this. I go back and I think about this.
كم هو رائع أن تفكر بهذا، ثم تعود للتفكير
Wednesday -- one Wednesday, when I was about 12 years old,
الأربعاء... ذات أربعاء عندما كنت في الثانية عشرة من عمري،
I didn't have a computer.
لم أكن أملك حاسوباَ
On Thursday, I had a computer.
الخميس... حصلت على واحد!
Can you imagine that change?
هل يمكنكم تخيل هذا التغيير؟
It's so drastic.
مؤثر جدا
I can't even think about anything that could change our lives that way.
حتى أنني لا يمكنني التفكير بشيء يمكنه تغيير حياتنا بهذه الطريقة.
But I'm actually not even going to talk about the computer.
لكن، أنا في الواقع لن أتحدث عن الحاسوب
I'm going to talk about a program that came loaded on that computer.
سأحدثكم عن برنامج يأتي محملا على الحاسوب
And it was build by, not the guy on the left,
وهو لم يبنى بواسطة الشخص الذي على اليسار
but the guy on the right.
بل الذي على اليمين
Does anybody know who the guy on the right is?
هل يوجد من يعرف الشاب على اليمين من يكون؟
Nobody ever knows the answer to this question.
لا يعرف أحد جواباَ عن هذا السؤال إطلاقاً
This is Bill Atkinson.
هذا "بيل أتكنسين"
And Bill Atkinson was responsible for tons of things
لقد كان "بيل أتكنسين" مسؤولاَ عن مئات الأشياء.
that you see on your computer every day.
التي تراها على جهازك يومياَ
But I want to talk about one program that Bill Atkinson wrote,
لكن أنا أريد التحدث عن برنامج واحد ألفه بيل أتكنسين،
called HyperCard.
يسمى "هايبر كارد"
Someone's cheering over there.
هناك من يصفق
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
HyperCard was a program that shipped with the Mac,
"هايبر كارد" كان برنامجا‘ يشحن مع"ماك"
and it was designed for users of the computer
وقد كان مصمماَ لمستخدمي الحاسوب،
to make programs on their computers.
وذلك لإنشاء البرامج على أجهزتهم
Crazy idea today.
تعد تلك فكرة جنونية اليوم!
And these programs were not the apps that we think about today,
وهذه البرامج ليست كالتطبيقات التي نفكر فيها اليوم.
with their large budgets and their big distribution.
بميزانيتهم الكبيرة وانتشارهم الواسع
These were small things,
كانت هذه البرامج أشياء صغيرة
people making applications to keep track of their local basketball team scores
ينشئ الناس التطبيقات ليتابعوا انتصارات فرق كرة السلة المحلية
or to organize their research
أو لتنظيم أبحاثهم
or to teach people about classical music
أو لتعليم الناس الموسيقى الكلاسيكية
or to calculate weird astronomical dates.
أو لحساب التواريخ الفلكية الغريبة
And then, of course, there were some art projects.
وبالتأكيد، فقد كان هنالك بعض المشاريع الفنية
This is my favorite one.
وهذا هو جزئي المفضل
It's called "If Monks Had Macs,"
يسمى " If Moncs Had Macs"
and it's a nonlinear kind of exploratory environment.
وهو نوع لا خطي من البيئة الاستكشافية
I thank the stars for HyperCard all of the time.
أشكر نجوم "هايبر كارد" كل الوقت
And I thank the stars for putting me in this era
وأشكر النجوم لوضعي في هذه الحقبة الزمنية!
where I got to use HyperCard.
حيث أمكنني استخدام "هايبر كارد"
HyperCard was the last program to ship on a public computer
لقد كان "هايبر كارد" البرنامج الأخير الذي يمكن نقله على جهاز الحاسوب العام
that was designed for the users of the computer to make programs with it.
كان مصمماَ لمستخدمي الحاسوب لإنشاء البرامج
If you talked to the people who invented the computer
لو كنتم تحدثتم إلى مخترعي الحاسوب
and you told them there would be a day, a magical day,
لأخبرتموهم بأنه سيأتي يوم سحري
when everybody had a computer but none of them knew how to program,
حيث يصبح لدى كل شخص حاسوب، لكن لا أحد منهم يعلم كيفية البرمجة
they would think you were crazy.
عندها سيظنون أنكم مجانين
So let's skip forward a few years.
لذا دعونا نتخطى بعض السنوات
I'm starting my career as an artist,
أنني أبدأ مهنتي كفنان
and I'm building things with my computer, small-scale things,
أبني أشياء باستخدام حاسوبي، على نطاق ضيق
investigating things like the growth systems of plants.
بالتحري عن أشياء أشياء كأنظمة نمو النباتات
Or, in this example, I'm building a simulated economy
أو، في هذا المثال، فأنا أصنع اقتصاداً محاكياً
in which pixels are trading color with one another,
فيما يعمل بيكسل في دمج الألون معاً،
trying to investigate how these types of systems work,
محاولاً التحقق من كيفية عمل هذه الأنظمة
and just kind of having fun.
وكنت مستمتعاً بوقتي نوعاً ما
And then this project led me to start working with data.
وهذا المشروع قادني إلى البدء في العمل على البيانات
So I'm building graphics like this,
لذلك فأنا أنشيء رسما بيانياً كهذا،
which compare "communism" --
الذي يقارن "الشيوعية"...
the frequency of usage of the word "communism" in the New York Times --
التكرار في أستخدام كلمة "الشيوعية" في صحيفة النيويورك تايمز
to "terrorism," at the top.
إلى" إلارهاب"، في أعلى القائمة.
You see "terrorism" kind of appears as "communism" is going away.
كما ترون "الإرهاب" تظهر نوعاً ما عندما تختفي "الشيوعية"
And with these graphics, I was really interested in the aesthetic of the graphs.
و هذة الرسومات، كنت مهتم جداً بشكلها الجمالي
This is Iran and Iraq.
هذه إيران والعراق
It reads like a clock. It's called a "timepiece graph."
تقرأ كساعة، تدعى "الرسم البياني الوقتي"
This is another timepiece graph, overlaying "despair" over "hope."
وهذه رسم بياني وقتي آخر، يغطي فيها "الياس" على"الأمل"
And there's only three times -- actually, it's "crisis" over "hope" --
وهناك في الحقيقة فقط ثلاث مرات، كانت "الإزمات" تتعدى" الأمل"
there's only three times when "crisis" eclipses "hope."
وهناك فقط ثلاث مرات، كانت "الأزمات" تتفوق على" الأمل"
We're in the middle of one of them right now.
نحن في منتصف واحدة منهم الآن
But don't think about that too much.
لكن لا تفكرون في هذا كثيراً
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And finally, the culmination of this work with the New York Times data
و أخيراً، تتويج هذه العمل مع بيانات نيويورك تايمز
a few years ago
منذ عدة سنوات
was the attempt to combine an entire year's news cycle
كانت محاولة دمج دورة أخبار السنة
into a single graphic.
في رسم بياني واحد
So these graphics actually show us a full year of news, all the people,
هذة الرسوم في الحقيقة ترينا أخبار سنة كاملة، كل الناس،
and how they're connected into a single graphic.
وكيف هم مرتبطين في رسم بياني واحد
And from there, I started to be interested again in more active systems.
ومن هناك، بدأت بالاهتمام مرة أخرى في نظام أكثر نشاطاً
Here's a project called "Just Landed,"
إذن هنا مشروع يدعى "للتو هبطت"
where I'm looking at people tweeting on Twitter.
بينما أنا أبحث في الناس الذي يغردون على التويتر
"Hey! I just landed in Hawaii!" -- you know,
"مرحباً، أنا للتو وصلت إلى هاواوي، تعلمون
how people just casually try to sneak that into their Twitter conversation.
كيف الناس بشكل عفوي يحاولون إدخال ذلك في محادثاتهم في التويتر
"I'm not showing off. Really. But I did just land in Hawaii."
"أنا لست استعرض. حقيقة لكن أنا فعلاً للتو هبطت في هاواي"
And then I'm plotting those people's trips,
وثم أنا أتخيل رحلة هؤلاء الناس
in the hopes that maybe we can use social network
في الأمل أنه يمكننا استخدام برامج وسائل التواصل الاجتماعي
and the data that it leaves behind
والبيانات التي تترك بالخلف
to provide a model of how people move,
لتقديم نموذج عن كيفية تحركات الناس،
which would be valuable to epidemiologists, among other people.
والذي يمكن أن يكون مفيد إلى علماء الأوبئة، بين اشخاص آخرين.
And, more fun -- this is a similar project,
ومزيد من المتعة هذا مشروع مشابه
looking at people saying "Good morning" to each other
مراقبة الناس الذي يقولون "صباح الخير" لبعضهم البعض
all around the world.
حول العالم.
Which taught me, by the way,
الذي علمني، بالمناسبة،
that it is true that people in Vancouver on the West Coast wake up much later
أنه صحيح الناس في فانكوفر علي الساحل الغربي يستيقظون متاخرًا جدًا
and say "Good morning" much later
ويقولون "صباح الخير" متاخر جداً
than the people on the East Coast,
مقارنة بالناس في الساحل الشرقي
who are more adventurous.
الذين يعتبرون أكثر مغامرة.
Here's a more useful -- maybe -- project,
هنا بعض النقاط المهمة التي ممكن أن تكون مهمة في المشروع
where I took all the information from the Kepler Project
الذي أخذت منه كل المعلومات "مشروع كيلبر"
and tried to put it into some visual form that made sense to me.
وحاولت وضعه في نظرة تكون أكثر منطيقة بالنسبة لي
And I should say that everything I've shown you up to now --
وهنا يجب أن أقول كل الأشياء التي أريتكم حتى الآن
these are all things that I just did for fun.
هي أشياء فعلتها فقط بدافع المتعة
It may seem weird, but this comes back from HyperCard.
ممكن أن يبدو غريباً ولكن هذه يعود من هايبر كارد
I'm building tools for myself.
أنا أبني أدوات لنفسي
I may share them with a few other people,
ممكن أن أتشاركهم مع قليل من الناس
but they're for fun, they're for me.
لكنهم للمتعة، أنهم لي
So, all these tools I show you kind of occupy this weird space
إذن، كل هذه الأدوات التي أريتكم نوعاً ما تحدث في هذا الفضاء الغريب
somewhere between science, art and design.
مكاناً ما بين العلم، الفن والتصميم.
That's where my practice lies.
هذه ما يعتمد عليه تدريبي
And still today, from my experience with HyperCard,
وإلى اليوم، من خبرتي مع الهايبر كارد
what I'm doing is building visual tools to help me understand systems.
ما أفعله هو أنني أبنى أداة مرئية لمساعدتي في فهم النظام
So today, I work at the New York Times.
إذن اليوم، أنا أعمل في النيويورك تايمز
I'm the data artist in residence at the New York Times.
أنا فني البيانات في مقر النيويورك تايمز
And I've had an opportunity at the Times
وكانت لدي الفرصة في التايمز
to work on a variety of really interesting projects,
للعمل على مجموعة مختلفة من المشاريع المثيرة للاهتمام
two of which I'm going to share with you today.
اثنان منها سأقوم بمشاركتها معكم اليوم
The first one, I've been working on in conjunction with Mark Hansen.
الأول، كنت أعمل عليها بالتزامن مع مارك هانسن.
Mark Hansen is a professor of statistics at UCLA. He's also a media artist.
مارك هانسن بروفسور إحصاء في جامعة كاليفورنيا، هو ايضاً فني اعلامي
And Mark came to the Times with a very interesting question
مارك قدم إلى التايمز بسؤال مثير للاهتمام
to what may seem like an obvious problem:
لشيء قد يبدو كمشكلة واضحة
When people share content on the internet,
عندما يتشاركون الناس المحتوى على الإنترنت،
how does that content get from person A to person B?
كيف هذه المعلومات تنتقل من الشخص ألف الى الشخص باء
Or maybe, person A to person B to person C to person D?
أو ربما، الشخص ألف إلى الشخص ب إلى الشخص س إلى الشخص د
We know that people share content in the internet,
نعلم أن الناس يتشاركون المحتوى على الإنترنت،
but what we don't know is what happens in that gap
ولكن الذي لا نعلمه ما الذي يحصل في الفراغ
between one person to the other.
ما بين الشخص الأول إلى الآخر
So we decided to build the tool to explore that,
لذا قررنا بناء أداة لاكشاف ذلك،
and this tool is called Cascade.
وهذه الأداة تدعى "Cascade".
If we look at these systems
إذا نظرنا إلى لهذه الأنظمة
that start with one event that leads to other events,
التي تبدأ بحدث واحد يقود إلى حدث آخر،
we call that structure a cascade.
نحن ندعي هذا الهيكل ب" cascade".
And these cascades actually happen over time.
هذه "cascade" تحدث مع مرور الوقت.
So we can model these things over time.
إذن نستطيع نمذجة هذه الأشياء مع مرور الوقت
Now, the New York Times has a lot of people who share our content,
الآن، النيويورك تايمز لديها الكثير من الناس الذي يشاركون محتوانا
so the cascades do not look like that one, they look more like this.
إذن "cascades" لا تبدو كهذه، تبدو كهذه أكثر.
Here's a typical cascade.
إليكم هنا cascade النموذجية
At the bottom left, the very first event.
في أسفل اليسار، الحدث الأول.
And then as people are sharing the content from one person to another,
و بينما الناس يتشاركون المحتوى من شخص لآخر
we go up in the Y axis, degrees of separation,
نذهب في المحور ص، درجات الانفصال،
and over on the X axis, for time.
والمحور X، لبعض الوقت
So we're able to look at that conversation in a couple of different views:
لذا نحن قادرون على رؤية المحادثات في أكثر من وجهه نظر
this one, which shows us the threads of conversation,
هذه، ترينا تسلسل المحادثات
and this one, which combines that stacked view
وهذه، ترينا وجهات النظر المتكدسة
with a view that lets us see the threads.
مع وجهه النظر التي جعلتنا نرى السلسلة
Now, the Times publishes about 7,000 pieces of content
الآن، التايمز تنشر تقريباً 7000 قطعة من المحتوى
every month.
كل شهر.
So it was important for us, when we were building this tool,
إذن، كان من المهم لنا، عندما كنا نبني هذه الاداة
to make it an exploratory one,
لجعلها أداة استكشافية.
so that people could dig through this vast terrain of data.
لذا الناس ممكن أن يحفرون خلال هذه التضاريس الشاسعة من البيانات.
I think of it as a vehicle that we're giving people
أفكر فيها كسيارة نعطيها للناس
to traverse this really big terrain of data.
لاجتياز هذه الكمية الكبيرة من البيانات.
So here's what it really looks like,
لذا هذا ما يبدو عليه فعلاً
and here's the cascade playing in real time.
وهنا "cascade" تلعب في الوقت الحقيقي.
I have to say, this was a tremendous moment.
يجب أن أقول، هذه كانت لحظة هائلة.
We had been working with canned data, fake data, for so long,
كنا نعمل على بيانات مختلقة، بيانات مزورة، لوقت طويل.
that when we saw this for the first moment,
هذا عندما رأينا هذا في اللحظة الأولى،
it was like an archaeologist who had just dusted off these dinosaur bones.
كان كعالم آثار للتو نفض غبار عظام الديناصورات
We discovered this thing, and we were seeing it for the first time,
نحن اكتشفنا هذا الشيء، ورأيناه للمره الأولى،
these sharing structures that underlie the internet.
هذه هياكل المشاركة التي تكمن وراء الإنترنت.
And maybe the dinosaur analogy is a good one,
وربما تشبيه الديناصورات جيد
because we're actually making some probabilistic guesses
لأننا في الحقيقة نقوم ببعض التخمين الإحتمالي
about how these things link.
حول كيفية ارتباط هذه الأشياء
We're looking at some of these pieces and making some guesses,
نحن نبحث عن بعض هذه القطع ونفرض افتراضات،
but we try to make sure that those are as statistically rigorous as possible.
ولكن نحن نحاول أن نتاكد بأن هذه القطع دقيقة إحصائيًا قدر الإمكان.
Now tweets, in this case, they become parts of stories.
التغريدات الحالية، في هذه الحالة، يصحبون جزءاً من القصة.
They become parts of narratives.
تصبح أجزاء من الروايات.
So we are building histories here,
إذن نحن نبني قصص هنا،
but they're very short-term histories.
ولكنها قصص قصيرة جداً.
And sometimes these very large cascades are the most interesting ones,
وأحياناً تكون cascades الكبيرة هي الأكثر إثارة للاهتمام
but sometimes the small ones are also interesting.
ولكن بعض الأحيان الصغيرة منها أيضاً مثيرة للاهتمام
This is one of my favorites. We call this the "Rabbi Cascade."
هذه واحدة من مفضلاتي ندعوها ""Rabbi Cascade".
It's a conversation amongst rabbis about this article in the New York Times,
هي محادثات بين علماء يهود حول مقالة في النيويورك تايمز،
about the fact that religious workers don't get a lot of time off.
عن الحقيقة حول علماء الدين لا يحصلون على أيام راحة كثيرة
I guess Saturdays and Sundays are bad days for them to take off.
أعتقد أن السبت والأحد أيام سيئة لهم لأخذ أجازة
So, in this cascade, there's a group of rabbis having a conversation
لذلك، في cascade، هناك مجموعة علماء يهود يتحدثون
about a New York Times story.
عن قصة النويورك تايمز
One of them has the best Twitter name ever --
واحد منهم لديه أفضل اسم في التويتر
he's called "The Velveteen Rabbi."
يدعى "عالم يهودي مخملي"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But we would have never found this if it weren't for this exploratory tool.
ولكن كان ممكن ألا نجدها لو لم نملك هذه الأداة الاستكشافية.
This would just be sitting somewhere,
كانت ستجلس في مكان ماً،
and we would have never been able to see that.
وسيكون من المستحيل أن نرى هذا
But this exercise of taking single pieces of information
ولكن هذا التدريب لأخذ قطعة واحدة من المعلومات
and building narrative structures, building histories out of them,
ونبني هيكل رواية، ونبني تاريخ منها،
I find tremendously interesting.
وجدته جدًا مثير للاهتمام.
You know, I moved to New York about two years ago.
أتعلمون، لقد انتقلت إلى نيويورك منذ سنتين
And in New York, everybody has a story
وفي نيويورك، كل شخص لديه قصة
that surrounds this tremendously impactful event
هذا يحيط بذاك ويؤثر عليه بشكل كبير
that happened on September 11 of 2001.
حدث هذا في سبتمر 11 عام 2001
And my own story with September 11 has really become a more intricate one,
وقصتي مع سبتمر 11 اصبحت جدًا معقدة،
because I spent a great deal of time
لأني أنفقت عليها الكثير من الوقت
working on a piece of the 9/11 Memorial in Manhattan.
للعمل على قطعة من النصب التذكاري 9/11 في مانهاتن
The central idea about the 9/11 Memorial
الفكرة الرئيسية للنصب التذكاري 9/11
is that the names in the memorial are not laid out in alphabetical order
هو أن الأسماء في النصب التذكاري لم ترتب بشكل أبجدي
or chronological order,
أو ترتيب زمني،
but instead, they're laid out in a way
لكن بدلاً من ذلك، يتم وضعها بطريقة ما
in which the relationships between the people who were killed
بحسب العلاقات بين الأشخاص الذين قتلو
are embodied in the memorial.
تتجسد في النصب التذكاري.
Brothers are placed next to brothers,
الإخوان وضعوا بجانب الإخوان،
coworkers are placed together.
زملاء العمل بجانب بعض.
So this memorial actually considers all of these myriad connections
إذن، هذا النصب التذكاري بالاساس يأخذ في الإعتبار كل هذه الروابط اللانهائية.
that were part of these people's lives.
نحن جزءاً من حياة هؤلاء الناس
I worked with a company called Local Projects
عملت مع شركة تدعى "Local projects"
to work on an algorithm and a software tool
للعمل على الخوارزمية والأداة البرمجيه
to help the architects build the layout for the memorial:
لمساعده المهندسين لبناء مخطط للنصب التذكاري
almost 3,000 names
حوالي 300 اسم
and almost 1,500 of these adjacency requests,
وتقريباً 1500 منهم بمحاذاة هذه الطلبات
these requests for connection --
هذه الطلبات للاتصال
so a very dense story, a very dense narrative,
إذن قصة ثقيلة جداً، أو رواية ثقيلة جداً
that becomes an embodied part of this memorial.
تصبح جزء يتجسد من هذا النصب التذكاري
Working with Jake Barton, we produce the software tool,
عملت مع جاك بارتون، قمنا بانتاج الأداة البرمجية
which allows the architects to, first of all, generate a layout
الذي سمح للمهندسين، أولاً، بإنتاج المخطط
that satisfied all of those adjacency requests,
يرضي كل الطلبات المحاذية
but then second, make little adjustments where they needed to
ولكن ثانياً، إقامة قليل من التعديلات في ما يحتاجونه
to tell the stories that they wanted to tell.
لإخبار القصص التي يريدون أن يخبروها
So this memorial, I think, has an incredibly timely concept
إذن هذا النصب التذكاري، كما اعتقد، لديه مفهوم توقيت مذهل
in our era of social networks,
في عصرنا من الشبكات الإجتماعية
because these networks -- these real-life networks that make up people's lives --
لأن هذة الشبكات -- هي الحياة الحقيقة التي تخلق حياة هؤلاء الناس
are actually embodied inside of the memorial.
يجسد فعلاً داخل هذا النصب التذكاري
And one of the most tremendously moving experiences
وواحد من أعظم التجارب المتحركة
is to go to the memorial
هو للذهاب إلى هذا النصب التذكاري
and see how these people are placed next to each other,
ورؤيه كيف هؤلاء الناس موضوعه بجانب بعضها البعض
so that this memorial is representing their own lives.
إذن هذا النصب التذكاري يمثل حياتهم الخاصة
How does this affect our lives?
كيف يمكن أن يؤثر هذا على حياتنا؟
Well, I don't know if you remember,
حسناً، لا أدري إذا كنتم تذكرون
but in the spring, there was a controversy,
ولكن في ذلك الربيع كان هناك ذاك الجدل
because it was discovered that on the iPhone
لأن الربيع الذي اكتشف فيه الأيفون
and, actually, on your computer,
وفي الحقيقة، في حواسيبكم
we were storing a tremendous amount of the location data.
نحن كنا نخزن كم هائل من البيانات المكانية
So Apple responded, saying, this was not location data about you,
لذلك أبل ردت بقولها هذه لم تكن معلومات موقعية عنك
it was location data about wireless networks
كانت معلومات موقعية عن الشبكات اللاسلكية
that were in the area where you are.
في المكان الذي كنت فيه
So it's not about you,
لذا إنها ليست عنك
but it's about where you are.
ولكنها عن أين كنت
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This is very valuable data.
هذه معلومات مفيدة جداً
It's like gold to researchers, this human-mobility data.
كأنه الذهب للباحثين هذه البيانات الحركية البشرية
So we thought, "Man! How many people have iPhones?"
لذا فكرت" يارجل كم من شخص لدية هاتف"؟
How many of you have iPhones?
كم منكم لديه هاتف؟
So in this room, we have this tremendous database of location data
في هذه الغرفة لدينا كم هائل من هذه البيانات الموقعيه
that researchers would really, really like.
هؤلاء الباحثين يودون فعلاً ذلك
So we built this system called Open Paths,
لذلك نحن بنينا نظام يدعى Open Paths،
which lets people upload their iPhone data
الذي يدع الناس يحملون بيانات iPhone الخاصة بهم
and broker relationships with researchers to share that data,
وسيط علاقات وباحثين يتشاركون البيانات،
to donate that data to people that can actually put it to use.
للتبرع بهذه البيانات للناس الذين يستخدمونها
Open Paths was a great success as a prototype.
فتح الطرق كان نجاح كنموذج أولي
We received thousands of data sets,
استلمنا اللآلاف من مجموعات البيانات
and we built this interface
وبنينا هذه الواجهه
which allows people to actually see their lives unfolding
التي تسمح للناس برؤية حياتهم تنتشر
from these traces that are left behind on your devices.
من هذه الآثار التي تخلفها في أجهزتكم
Now, what we didn't expect was how moving this experience would be.
الآن، الذي لا نستطيع توقعه هو كيف ستكون هذه التجربة
When I uploaded my data, I thought, "Big deal.
عندما رفعت بياناتي اعتقدت "مسأله كبرى"
I know where I live. I know where I work. What am I going to see here?"
أعرف أين أعيش، أعرف أين أعمل. ماذا سأرى هنا؟
Well, it turns out, what I saw was that moment I got off the plane
حسناً، في المقابل،
to start my new life in New York;
لبدء حياتي الجديدة في نيويورك
the restaurant where I had Thai food that first night,
المطعم الذي أكلت فيه أكل تايلندي أول ليلة
thinking about this new experience of being in New York;
أفكر في هذه التجربة الجديدة للتواجد في نيويورك
the day that I met my girlfriend.
اليوم الذي قابلت فيه حبيبتي
This is LaGuardia airport.
في مطار لاجورديا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
This is this Thai restaurant on Amsterdam Avenue.
هذا هو المطعم التايلندي في أمستردام أفينيو
This is the moment I met my girlfriend.
هذه هي اللحظة التي قابلت فيها حبيبتي
See how that changes the first time I told you about those stories
انظروا كيف غير هذا أول مره أخبرتكم بهذه القصص
and the second time I told you about those stories?
وفي المره الثانية أخبرتكم بهذه القصص؟
Because what we do in the tool, inadvertently,
لأن ما نفعله في هذه الأداة، من غير قصد،
is we put these pieces of data into a human context.
هو أننا نضع هذه القطع من البيانات في سياق يناسب الإنسان
And by placing data into a human context,
وبوضع هذه البيانات بهذا الشكل
it gains meaning.
تصبح لها معنى
And I think this is tremendously, tremendously important,
وأعتقد أن هذا مهم جدا
because these are our histories that are being stored on these devices.
لأن هذا تاريخنا الذي يُخزن في هذه الأجهزة
And by thinking about them that way,
وبالتفكير بهم بهذه الطريقة
putting them in a human context --
وضعهم في سياق مفهوم
first of all, what we do with our own data is get a better understanding
في البداية، ما نفعله في بياناتنا في فهمهم بشكل أفضل
of the type of information that we're sharing.
في أنواع المعلومات التي نتشاركها
But if we can do this with other data, if we can put data into a human context,
ولكن إذا استطعنا فعل ذلك مع بيانات اخرى، لو استطعنا وضع البيانات بسياق مفهوم
I think we can change a lot of things,
أعتقد أننا نستطيع تغيير أشياء كثيرة،
because it builds, automatically, empathy for the people involved in these systems.
لأنه يبني بشكل تلقائي التعاطف من الناس الذين يشاركون في هذا النظام
And that, in turn, results in a fundamental respect,
وهذا، بالمقابل، ينتج عن احترام أساسي
which, I believe, is missing in a large part of technology,
مما يعني كما اؤمن، مفقود في جزء كبير من تكنولوجيا
when we start to deal with issues like privacy,
عندما بدأنا التعامل مع مشاكل مثل الخصوصية
by understanding that these numbers are not just numbers,
بفهم أن هذه الأرقام ليست فقط أرقام
but instead they're attached, tethered to, pieces of the real world.
ولكن بالعكس مرتبطين، إلى أجزاء من العالم
They carry weight.
يحملون وزن
By understanding that, the dialog becomes a lot different.
بفهم هذا يصبح الحوار مختلف جداً
How many of you have ever clicked a button
كم واحد منكم نقر على الزر مره في حياته
that enables a third party to access your location data on your phone?
هذا يسمح لطرف ثالث الدخول في المعلومات المكانية في هواتفكم ؟
Lots of you.
الكثير منكم
So the third party is the developer,
الطرف الثالث هو المطور
the second party is Apple.
الطرف الثاني هو أبل
The only party that never gets access to this information is the first party!
الطرف الوحيد الذي لا يحصل على هذه المعلومات هو أول طرف
And I think that's because we think about these pieces of data
وأعتقد أن هذا بسبب أننا نفكر في هذه الأجزاء من البيانات
in this stranded, abstract way.
بهذا الشكل العادي، المختصر
We don't put them into a context
لا نضعهم في سياقات
which, I think, makes them a lot more important.
بمعنى كما أعتقد نجعلهم أكثر أهمية
So what I'm asking you to do is really simple:
إذن ما طُلب منكم فعله شيء بسيط
start to think about data in a human context.
ابدأو في التفكير في البيانات بسياق مفهوم
It doesn't really take anything.
في الحقيقة أنه لا يأخذ منكم شيئاً
When you read stock prices, think about them in a human context.
عندما تقرأ أسعار السندات، تفكر فيها بطريقة إنسانية
When you think about mortgage reports,
عندما تفكر في تقارير الرهن العقاري، فكر فيها بسياق إنساني
There's no doubt that big data is big business.
مما لا شك فيه أن البيانات الكبيرة تعنى تجارة كبيرة
There's an industry being developed here.
هناك صناعة يجري تطويرها هنا
Think about how well we've done
فكر في مدى نجاحنا
in previous industries that we've developed involving resources.
في الصناعات السابقة التي طورناها من خلال المصادر
Not very well at all.
ليست جيداً على الاطلاق
I think part of that problem is, we've had a lack of participation in these dialogues
أعتقد جزء من هذه المشكله هو، أنه كان لدينا نقص في الحضور في هذه الحوار
from multiple pieces of human society.
من أجزاء متعدده في المجتمع البشري
So the other thing that I'm asking for
لذا الشي الثاني الذي أطلبه
is an inclusion in this dialogue from artists, from poets, from writers --
هو تضمين في هذه الحوار من الفنانين، الشعراء، ومن الكتاب
from people who can bring a human element into this discussion.
من الناس الذين سيجلبون عناصر إنسانية الى هذه المناقشة
Because I believe that this world of data
لأنني أؤمن بأن هذا العالم من البيانات
is going to be transformative for us.
سيصبح نقطة تحول لنا
And unlike our attempts with the resource industry
وبعكس محاولاتنا مع صناعه الموارد
and our attempts with the financial industry,
ومحاولاتنا مع الصناعات المالية
by bringing the human element into this story,
بإحضار عناصر إنسانية لهذه القصه
I think we can take it to tremendous places.
أعتقد أننا نستطيع أخذه إلى أماكن مهمة
Thank you.
شكراً
(Applause)
(تصفيق)